<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2024//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_240101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39258424</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1467-3010</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Nutrition bulletin</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Nutr Bull</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Mediterranean diet for the management of metabolic dysfunction-associated steatotic liver disease in non-Mediterranean, Western countries: What's known and what's needed?</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/nbu.12707</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Metabolic dysfunction-associated steatotic liver disease (MASLD) is the most common liver disease worldwide, affecting 30% of the population in Western countries. MASLD is considered the hepatic manifestation of the metabolic syndrome, pathophysiologically underpinned by insulin resistance and frequently co-exists with hypertension, central obesity and dyslipidaemia. Currently, safe and effective pharmacotherapies for MASLD are limited, making weight loss with lifestyle changes the mainstay therapy. A Mediterranean diet (MedDiet) has emerged as an effective dietary pattern for preventing and managing MASLD, but most studies have been conducted in Mediterranean countries, necessitating further investigation into its benefits in Western populations. Additionally, the effect of holistic multimodal lifestyle interventions, including physical activity combined with the MedDiet, is not well established. Finally, MASLD's widespread prevalence and rapid growth require improved accessibility to interventions. Digital health delivery platforms, designed for remote access, could be a promising approach to providing timely support to individuals with MASLD. This narrative review summarises the current evidence related to the effects of the MedDiet in Western, multicultural populations with MASLD. This includes a detailed description of the composition, prescription and adherence to dietary interventions in terms of how they have been designed and applied. The evidence related to the role of physical activity or exercise interventions prescribed in combination with the MedDiet for MASLD will also be reviewed. Finally, recommendations for the design and delivery of dietary and physical activity or exercise interventions to inform the design of future randomised controlled trials to facilitate the optimal management of MASLD are outlined.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2024 The Author(s). Nutrition Bulletin published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of British Nutrition Foundation.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sualeheen</LastName><ForeName>Ayesha</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition, School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences, Deakin University, Geelong, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tan</LastName><ForeName>Sze-Yen</ForeName><Initials>SY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition, School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences, Deakin University, Geelong, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Georgousopoulou</LastName><ForeName>Ekavi</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Discipline of Nutrition and Dietetics, Faculty of Health, University of Canberra, Canberra, New South Wales, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Daly</LastName><ForeName>Robin M</ForeName><Initials>RM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition, School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences, Deakin University, Geelong, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tierney</LastName><ForeName>Audrey C</ForeName><Initials>AC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Allied Health, Centre for Implementation Research, Health Research Institute, University of Limerick, Limerick, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Roberts</LastName><ForeName>Stuart K</ForeName><Initials>SK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gastroenterology, Alfred Health, Prahran, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Central Clinical School, Monash University, Clayton, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>George</LastName><ForeName>Elena S</ForeName><Initials>ES</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1385-2371</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition, School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences, Deakin University, Geelong, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Nutr Bull</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9315625</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1467-3010</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">MASLD</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mediterranean diet</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">NAFLD</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">digital health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fatty liver</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lifestyle</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39258424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/nbu.12707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abe, R.A.M., Masroor, A., Khorochkov, A., Prieto, J., Singh, K.B., Nnadozie, M.C. et&#xa0;al. (2021) The role of vitamins in non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease: a systematic review. Cureus, 13(8), e16855. Available from: https://doi.org/10.7759/cureus.16855</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arranz, S., Chiva&#x2010;Blanch, G., Valderas&#x2010;Mart&#xed;nez, P., Medina&#x2010;Rem&#xf3;n, A., Lamuela&#x2010;Ravent&#xf3;s, R.M. &amp; Estruch, R. (2012) Wine, beer, alcohol and polyphenols on cardiovascular disease and cancer. Nutrients, 4(7), 759&#x2013;781. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3390/nu4070759</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assy, N., Nassar, F., Nasser, G. &amp; Grosovski, M. (2009) Olive oil consumption and non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease. World Journal of Gastroenterology, 15(15), 1809&#x2013;1815. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3748/wjg.15.1809</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bach&#x2010;Faig, A., Berry, E.M., Lairon, D., Reguant, J., Trichopoulou, A., Dernini, S. et&#xa0;al. (2011) Mediterranean diet pyramid today. Science and cultural updates. Public Health Nutrition, 14(12A), 2274&#x2013;2284. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1017/S1368980011002515</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bassi, N., Karagodin, I., Wang, S., Vassallo, P., Priyanath, A., Massaro, E. et&#xa0;al. (2014) Lifestyle modification for metabolic syndrome: a systematic review. The American Journal of Medicine, 127(12), 1242.e1&#x2013;1242.e10. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amjmed.2014.06.035</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bowden Davies, K.A., Sprung, V.S., Norman, J.A., Thompson, A., Mitchell, K.L., Harrold, J.O.A. et&#xa0;al. (2019) Physical activity and sedentary time: association with metabolic health and liver fat. Medicine and Science in Sports and Exercise, 51(6), 1169&#x2013;1177. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1249/MSS.0000000000001901</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carr, R.M., Oranu, A. &amp; Khungar, V. (2016) Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: pathophysiology and management. Gastroenterology Clinics of North America, 45(4), 639&#x2013;652. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gtc.2016.07.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Croci, I., Coombes, J.S., Bucher Sandbakk, S., Keating, S.E., Nauman, J., Macdonald, G.A. et&#xa0;al. (2019) Non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease: prevalence and all&#x2010;cause mortality according to sedentary behaviour and cardiorespiratory fitness. The HUNT study. Progress in Cardiovascular Diseases, 62(2), 127&#x2013;134. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pcad.2019.01.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis, J.N., L&#xea;, K.A., Walker, R.W., Vikman, S., Spruijt&#x2010;Metz, D., Weigensberg, M.J. et&#xa0;al. (2010) Increased hepatic fat in overweight Hispanic youth influenced by interaction between genetic variation in PNPLA3 and high dietary carbohydrate and sugar consumption. The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 92(6), 1522&#x2013;1527. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3945/ajcn.2010.30185</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinu, M., Pagliai, G., Casini, A. &amp; Sofi, F. (2018) Mediterranean diet and multiple health outcomes: an umbrella review of meta&#x2010;analyses of observational studies and randomised trials. European Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 72(1), 30&#x2013;43. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1038/ejcn.2017.58</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donnelly, K.L., Smith, C.I., Schwarzenberg, S.J., Jessurun, J., Boldt, M.D. &amp; Parks, E.J. (2005) Sources of fatty acids stored in liver and secreted via lipoproteins in patients with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. The Journal of Clinical Investigation, 115(5), 1343&#x2013;1351. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1172/jci23621</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dyson, J.K., Anstee, Q.M. &amp; McPherson, S. (2014) Non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease: a practical approach to diagnosis and staging. Frontline Gastroenterology, 5(3), 211&#x2013;218. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1136/flgastro&#x2010;2013&#x2010;100403</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Association for the Study of the Liver, European Association for the Study of Diabetes &amp; European Association for the Study of Obesity. (2016) EASL&#x2010;EASD&#x2010;EASO clinical practice guidelines for the Management of non&#x2010;Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease. Obesity Facts, 9(2), 65&#x2013;90. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1159/000443344</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feidantsis, K., Methenitis, S., Ketselidi, K., Vagianou, K., Skepastianos, P., Hatzitolios, A. et&#xa0;al. (2021) Comparison of short&#x2010;term hypocaloric high&#x2010;protein diets with a hypocaloric Mediterranean diet: effect on body composition and health&#x2010;related blood markers in overweight and sedentary young participants. Nutrition, 91&#x2010;92, 111365. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nut.2021.111365</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franco, I., Bianco, A., Mirizzi, A., Campanella, A., Bonfiglio, C., Sorino, P. et&#xa0;al. (2021) Physical activity and low glycemic index Mediterranean diet: main and modification effects on NAFLD score. Results from a randomized clinical trial. Nutrients, 13(1), 66.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, V., Long, M.T., Singh, S.R., Kim, Y., Zhang, X., Rogers, G. et&#xa0;al. (2023) A healthy diet is associated with a lower risk of hepatic fibrosis. The Journal of Nutrition, 153(5), 1587&#x2013;1596. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tjnut.2023.03.038</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>George, E.S., Forsyth, A.K., Reddy, A., Itsiopoulos, C., Roberts, S.K., Nicoll, A.J. et&#xa0;al. (2023) A Mediterranean and low&#x2010;fat dietary intervention in non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease patients: exploring participant experience and perceptions about dietary change. Journal of Human Nutrition and Dietetics, 36(3), 592&#x2013;602. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1111/jhn.13069</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>George, E.S., Kucianski, T., Mayr, H.L., Moschonis, G., Tierney, A.C. &amp; Itsiopoulos, C. (2018) A Mediterranean diet model in Australia: strategies for translating the traditional Mediterranean diet into a multicultural setting. Nutrients, 10(4), 465. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3390/nu10040465</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>George, E.S., Reddy, A., Nicoll, A.J., Ryan, M.C., Itsiopoulos, C., Abbott, G. et&#xa0;al. (2022) Impact of a Mediterranean diet on hepatic and metabolic outcomes in non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease: the MEDINA randomised controlled trial. Liver International, 42(6), 1308&#x2013;1322. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1111/liv.15264</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haigh, L., Bremner, S., Houghton, D., Henderson, E., Avery, L., Hardy, T. et&#xa0;al. (2019) Barriers and facilitators to Mediterranean diet adoption by patients with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease in northern Europe. Clinical Gastroenterology and Hepatology, 17(7), 1364&#x2013;1371.e1363. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cgh.2018.10.044</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hallsworth, K., Thoma, C., Moore, S., Ploetz, T., Anstee, Q.M., Taylor, R. et&#xa0;al. (2015) Non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease is associated with higher levels of objectively measured sedentary behaviour and lower levels of physical activity than matched healthy controls. Frontline Gastroenterology, 6(1), 44&#x2013;51. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1136/flgastro&#x2010;2014&#x2010;100432</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassani Zadeh, S., Mansoori, A. &amp; Hosseinzadeh, M. (2021) Relationship between dietary patterns and non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease: a systematic review and meta&#x2010;analysis. Journal of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, 36(6), 1470&#x2013;1478. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1111/jgh.15363</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holl&#xe6;nder, P.L.B., Ross, A.B. &amp; Kristensen, M. (2015) Whole&#x2010;grain and blood lipid changes in apparently healthy adults: a systematic review and meta&#x2010;analysis of randomized controlled studies123. The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 102(3), 556&#x2013;572. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3945/ajcn.115.109165</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huber, Y., Pfirrmann, D., Gebhardt, I., Labenz, C., Gehrke, N., Straub, B.K. et&#xa0;al. (2019) Improvement of non&#x2010;invasive markers of NAFLD from an individualised, web&#x2010;based exercise program. Alimentary Pharmacology &amp; Therapeutics, 50(8), 930&#x2013;939. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1111/apt.15427</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hutchesson, M.J., Rollo, M.E., Krukowski, R., Ells, L., Harvey, J., Morgan, P.J. et&#xa0;al. (2015) eHealth interventions for the prevention and treatment of overweight and obesity in adults: a systematic review with meta&#x2010;analysis. Obesity Reviews, 16(5), 376&#x2013;392. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1111/obr.12268</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jarvis, H., O'Keefe, H., Craig, D., Stow, D., Hanratty, B. &amp; Anstee, Q.M. (2022) Does moderate alcohol consumption accelerate the progression of liver disease in NAFLD? A systematic review and narrative synthesis. BMJ Open, 12(1), e049767. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen&#x2010;2021&#x2010;049767</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson, N.A., Sachinwalla, T., Walton, D.W., Smith, K., Armstrong, A., Thompson, M.W. et&#xa0;al. (2009) Aerobic exercise training reduces hepatic and visceral lipids in obese individuals without weight loss. Hepatology, 50(4), 1105&#x2013;1112. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1002/hep.23129</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kempf, K., Altpeter, B., Berger, J., Reu&#xdf;, O., Fuchs, M., Schneider, M. et&#xa0;al. (2017) Efficacy of the Telemedical lifestyle intervention program TeLiPro in advanced stages of type 2 diabetes: a randomized controlled trial. Diabetes Care, 40(7), 863&#x2013;871. Available from: https://doi.org/10.2337/dc17&#x2010;0303</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalatbari&#x2010;Soltani, S., Imamura, F., Brage, S., De Lucia, R.E., Griffin, S.J., Wareham, N.J. et&#xa0;al. (2019) The association between adherence to the Mediterranean diet and hepatic steatosis: cross&#x2010;sectional analysis of two independent studies, the UK fenland study and the Swiss CoLaus study. BMC Medicine, 17(1), 19. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1186/s12916&#x2010;019&#x2010;1251&#x2010;7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan, J., Gul, P., Rashid, M.T., Li, Q. &amp; Liu, K. (2024) Composition of whole grain dietary fiber and phenolics and their impact on markers of inflammation. Nutrients, 16(7), 1047.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konerman, M.A., Walden, P., Joseph, M., Jackson, E.A., Lok, A.S. &amp; Rubenfire, M. (2019) Impact of a structured lifestyle programme on patients with metabolic syndrome complicated by non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease. Alimentary Pharmacology &amp; Therapeutics, 49(3), 296&#x2013;307. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1111/apt.15063</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kratz, M., Marcovina, S., Nelson, J.E., Yeh, M.M., Kowdley, K.V., Callahan, H.S. et&#xa0;al. (2014) Dairy fat intake is associated with glucose tolerance, hepatic and systemic insulin sensitivity, and liver fat but not &#x3b2;&#x2010;cell function in humans. The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 99(6), 1385&#x2013;1396. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3945/ajcn.113.075457</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, C.H., Fu, Y., Yang, S.J. &amp; Chi, C.C. (2020) Effects of Omega&#x2010;3 polyunsaturated fatty acid supplementation on non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver: a systematic review and meta&#x2010;analysis. Nutrients, 12(9), 2769. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3390/nu12092769</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, J.&#x2010;H., Lee, K.&#x2010;H., Kim, H.&#x2010;J., Youk, H. &amp; Lee, H.&#x2010;Y. (2022) Effective prevention and management tools for metabolic syndrome based on digital health&#x2010;based lifestyle interventions using healthcare devices. Diagnostics, 12(7), 1730. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3390/diagnostics12071730</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, X., He, M., Yi, X., Lu, X., Zhu, M., Xue, M. et&#xa0;al. (2024) Short&#x2010;chain fatty acids in nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: new prospects for short&#x2010;chain fatty acids as therapeutic targets. Heliyon, 10(5), e26991. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e26991</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luukkonen, P.K., S&#xe4;devirta, S., Zhou, Y., Kayser, B., Ali, A., Ahonen, L. et&#xa0;al. (2018) Saturated fat is more metabolically harmful for the human liver than unsaturated fat or simple sugars. Diabetes Care, 41(8), 1732&#x2013;1739. Available from: https://doi.org/10.2337/dc18&#x2010;0071</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, J., Hennein, R., Liu, C., Long, M.T., Hoffmann, U., Jacques, P.F. et&#xa0;al. (2018) Improved diet quality associates with reduction in liver fat, particularly in individuals with high genetic risk scores for nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. Gastroenterology, 155(1), 107&#x2013;117. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1053/j.gastro.2018.03.038</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malakou, E., Linardakis, M., Armstrong, M.E.G., Zannidi, D., Foster, C., Johnson, L. et&#xa0;al. (2018) The combined effect of promoting the Mediterranean diet and physical activity on metabolic risk factors in adults: a systematic review and meta&#x2010;analysis of randomised controlled trials. Nutrients, 10(11), 1577.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mart&#xed;nez&#x2010;Gonz&#xe1;lez, M., Hershey, M.S., Zazpe, I. &amp; Trichopoulou, A. (2017) Transferability of the Mediterranean diet to non&#x2010;Mediterranean countries. What is and what is not the Mediterranean diet. Nutrients, 9(11), 1226. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3390/nu9111226</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazzotti, A., Caletti, M.T., Brodosi, L., Di Domizio, S., Forchielli, M.L., Petta, S. et&#xa0;al. (2018) An internet&#x2010;based approach for lifestyle changes in patients with NAFLD: two&#x2010;year effects on weight loss and surrogate markers. Journal of Hepatology, 69(5), 1155&#x2013;1163. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhep.2018.07.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meex, R.C.R. &amp; Blaak, E.E. (2021) Mitochondrial dysfunction is a key pathway that links saturated fat intake to the development and progression of NAFLD. Molecular Nutrition &amp; Food Research, 65(1), e1900942. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1002/mnfr.201900942</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milesi, G., Rangan, A. &amp; Grafenauer, S. (2022) Whole grain consumption and inflammatory markers: a systematic literature review of randomized control trials. Nutrients, 14(2), 374.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mock, K., Lateef, S., Benedito, V.A. &amp; Tou, J.C. (2017) High&#x2010;fructose corn syrup&#x2010;55 consumption alters hepatic lipid metabolism and promotes triglyceride accumulation. The Journal of Nutritional Biochemistry, 39, 32&#x2013;39. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jnutbio.2016.09.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moosavian, S.P., Arab, A. &amp; Paknahad, Z. (2020) The effect of a Mediterranean diet on metabolic parameters in patients with non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease: a systematic review of randomized controlled trials. Clinical Nutrition ESPEN, 35, 40&#x2013;46. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.clnesp.2019.10.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nobili, V., Liccardo, D., Bedogni, G., Salvatori, G., Gnani, D., Bersani, I. et&#xa0;al. (2014) Influence of dietary pattern, physical activity, and I148M PNPLA3 on steatosis severity in at&#x2010;risk adolescents. Genes &amp; Nutrition, 9(3), 392. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1007/s12263&#x2010;014&#x2010;0392&#x2010;8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ock&#xe9;, M.C. (2013) Evaluation of methodologies for assessing the overall diet: dietary quality scores and dietary pattern analysis. The Proceedings of the Nutrition Society, 72(2), 191&#x2013;199. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1017/s0029665113000013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paik, J.M., Golabi, P., Younossi, Y., Mishra, A. &amp; Younossi, Z.M. (2020) Changes in the global burden of chronic liver diseases from 2012 to 2017: the growing impact of NAFLD. Hepatology, 72(5), 1605&#x2013;1616. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1002/hep.31173</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papadaki, A., Nolen&#x2010;Doerr, E. &amp; Mantzoros, C.S. (2020) The effect of the Mediterranean diet on metabolic health: a systematic review and meta&#x2010;analysis of controlled trials in adults. Nutrients, 12(11), 3342.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papadaki, A. &amp; Scott, J.A. (2008) Follow&#x2010;up of a web&#x2010;based tailored intervention promoting the Mediterranean diet in Scotland. Patient Education and Counseling, 73(2), 256&#x2013;263. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pec.2008.05.030</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Powell. (2021) Non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease. The Lancet, 397(10290), 2212&#x2013;2224. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/s0140&#x2010;6736(20)32511&#x2010;3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Properzi, C., O'Sullivan, T.A., Sherriff, J.L., Ching, H.L., Jeffrey, G.P., Buckley, R.F. et&#xa0;al. (2018) Ad libitum Mediterranean and low&#x2010;fat diets both significantly reduce hepatic steatosis: a randomized controlled trial. Hepatology, 68(5), 1741&#x2013;1754. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1002/hep.30076</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu, S., Cai, X., Sun, Z., Li, L., Z&#xfc;gel, M., Steinacker, J.M. et&#xa0;al. (2017) Association between physical activity and risk of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: a meta&#x2010;analysis. Therapeutic Advances in Gastroenterology, 10(9), 701&#x2013;713. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1177/1756283x17725977</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rinella, M.E., Lazarus, J.V., Ratziu, V., Francque, S.M., Sanyal, A.J., Kanwal, F. et&#xa0;al. (2023) A multisociety Delphi consensus statement on new fatty liver disease nomenclature. Hepatology, 78(6), 1966&#x2013;1986. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1097/hep.0000000000000520</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rinella, M.E., Neuschwander&#x2010;Tetri, B.A., Siddiqui, M.S., Abdelmalek, M.F., Caldwell, S., Barb, D. et&#xa0;al. (2023) AASLD practice guidance on the clinical assessment and management of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. Hepatology, 77(5), 1797&#x2013;1835. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1097/hep.0000000000000323</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ristic&#x2010;Medic, D., Kovacic, M., Takic, M., Arsic, A., Petrovic, S., Paunovic, M. et&#xa0;al. (2020) Calorie&#x2010;restricted Mediterranean and low&#x2010;fat diets affect fatty acid status in individuals with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. Nutrients, 13(1), 15. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3390/nu13010015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryan, M.C., Itsiopoulos, C., Thodis, T., Ward, G., Trost, N., Hofferberth, S. et&#xa0;al. (2013) The Mediterranean diet improves hepatic steatosis and insulin sensitivity in individuals with non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease. Journal of Hepatology, 59(1), 138&#x2013;143. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhep.2013.02.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salomone, F., Godos, J. &amp; Zelber&#x2010;Sagi, S. (2016) Natural antioxidants for non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease: molecular targets and clinical perspectives. Liver International, 36(1), 5&#x2013;20. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1111/liv.12975</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salomone, F., Ivancovsky&#x2010;Wajcman, D., Fliss&#x2010;Isakov, N., Webb, M., Grosso, G., Godos, J. et&#xa0;al. (2020) Higher phenolic acid intake independently associates with lower prevalence of insulin resistance and non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease. JHEP Reports, 2(2), 100069. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhepr.2020.100069</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sangouni, A.A., Hassani Zadeh, S., Mozaffari&#x2010;Khosravi, H. &amp; Hosseinzadeh, M. (2021) Effect of Mediterranean diet on liver enzymes: a systematic review and meta&#x2010;analysis of randomised controlled trials. British Journal of Nutrition, 128, 1231&#x2013;1239. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1017/S0007114521002270</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santoro, N., Savoye, M., Kim, G., Marotto, K., Shaw, M.M., Pierpont, B. et&#xa0;al. (2012) Hepatic fat accumulation is modulated by the interaction between the rs738409 variant in the PNPLA3 gene and the dietary omega6/omega3 PUFA intake. PLoS One, 7(5), e37827. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0037827</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah, R.V., Murthy, V.L., Allison, M.A., Ding, J., Budoff, M., Frazier&#x2010;Wood, A.C. et&#xa0;al. (2016) Diet and adipose tissue distributions: the multi&#x2010;ethnic study of atherosclerosis. Nutrition, Metabolism, and Cardiovascular Diseases, 26(3), 185&#x2013;193. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.numecd.2015.12.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shojaei&#x2010;Zarghani, S., Safarpour, A.R., Fattahi, M.R. &amp; Keshtkar, A. (2022) Sodium in relation with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease: a systematic review and meta&#x2010;analysis of observational studies. Food Science &amp; Nutrition, 10(5), 1579&#x2013;1591. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1002/fsn3.2781</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simopoulos, A.P. (2008) The importance of the Omega&#x2010;6/Omega&#x2010;3 fatty acid ratio in cardiovascular disease and other chronic diseases. Experimental Biology and Medicine, 233(6), 674&#x2013;688. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3181/0711&#x2010;MR&#x2010;311</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soriguer, F., Morcillo, S., Cardona, F., Rojo&#x2010;Mart&#xed;nez, G., de la Cruz, A.M., Ruiz de Adana, M.L. et&#xa0;al. (2006) Pro12Ala polymorphism of the PPARG2 gene is associated with type 2 diabetes mellitus and peripheral insulin sensitivity in a population with a high intake of oleic acid. The Journal of Nutrition, 136(9), 2325&#x2013;2330. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1093/jn/136.9.2325</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spooner, M.H. &amp; Jump, D.B. (2023) Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease and Omega&#x2010;3 fatty acids: mechanisms and clinical use. Annual Review of Nutrition, 43, 199&#x2013;223. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev&#x2010;nutr&#x2010;061021&#x2010;030223</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sterne, J.A.C., Savovi&#x107;, J., Page, M.J., Elbers, R.G., Blencowe, N.S., Boutron, I. et&#xa0;al. (2019) RoB 2: a revised tool for assessing risk of bias in randomised trials. BMJ, 366, l4898. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.l4898</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Susan, K., Joanna, H.S. &amp; Moore, J.B. (2017) Efficacy of dietary and physical activity intervention in non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease: a systematic review. BMJ Open Gastroenterology, 4(1), e000139. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjgast&#x2010;2017&#x2010;000139</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thoma, C., Day, C.P. &amp; Trenell, M.I. (2012) Lifestyle interventions for the treatment of non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease in adults: a systematic review. Journal of Hepatology, 56(1), 255&#x2013;266. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhep.2011.06.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian, T., Zhang, J., Xie, W., Ni, Y., Fang, X., Liu, M. et&#xa0;al. (2022) Dietary quality and relationships with metabolic dysfunction&#x2010;associated fatty liver disease (MAFLD) among United States adults, results from NHANES 2017&#x2010;2018. Nutrients, 14(21), 4505. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3390/nu14214505</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tr&#xe9;po, E., Romeo, S., Zucman&#x2010;Rossi, J. &amp; Nahon, P. (2016) PNPLA3 gene in liver diseases. Journal of Hepatology, 65(2), 399&#x2013;412. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhep.2016.03.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsartsou, E., Proutsos, N., Castanas, E. &amp; Kampa, M. (2019) Network meta&#x2010;analysis of metabolic effects of olive&#x2010;oil in humans shows the importance of olive oil consumption with moderate polyphenol levels as part of the Mediterranean diet. Frontiers in Nutrition, 6. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2019.00006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ushula, T.W., Mamun, A., Darssan, D., Wang, W.Y.S., Williams, G.M., Whiting, S.J. et&#xa0;al. (2022) Dietary patterns and the risks of metabolic syndrome and insulin resistance among young adults: evidence from a longitudinal study. Clinical Nutrition, 41(7), 1523&#x2013;1531. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.clnu.2022.05.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vetrani, C., Costabile, G., Luongo, D., Naviglio, D., Rivellese, A.A., Riccardi, G. et&#xa0;al. (2016) Effects of whole&#x2010;grain cereal foods on plasma short chain fatty acid concentrations in individuals with the metabolic syndrome. Nutrition, 32(2), 217&#x2013;221. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nut.2015.08.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, R., Yan, R., Jiao, J., Li, F., Zhang, H., Chang, Z. et&#xa0;al. (2024) Fruit and vegetable intake and the risk of non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease: a meta&#x2010;analysis of observational studies. Frontiers in Nutrition, 11, 1398184. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2024.1398184</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, S.&#x2010;t., Zheng, J., Peng, H.&#x2010;w., Cai, X.&#x2010;l., Pan, X.&#x2010;t., Li, H.&#x2010;q. et&#xa0;al. (2020) Physical activity intervention for non&#x2010;diabetic patients with non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease: a meta&#x2010;analysis of randomized controlled trials. BMC Gastroenterology, 20(1), 66. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1186/s12876&#x2010;020&#x2010;01204&#x2010;3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watzinger, C., Nonnenmacher, T., Grafetstatter, M., Sowah, S.A., Ulrich, C.M., Kauczor, H.U. et&#xa0;al. (2020) Dietary factors in relation to liver fat content: a cross&#x2010;sectional study. Nutrients, 12(3), 825. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3390/nu12030825</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weng, G. &amp; Dunn, W. (2019) Effect of alcohol consumption on nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. Translational Gastroenterology and Hepatology, 4, 70. Available from: https://doi.org/10.21037/tgh.2019.09.02</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong, R.J. &amp; Singal, A.K. (2020) Trends in liver disease etiology among adults awaiting liver transplantation in the United States, 2014&#x2010;2019. JAMA Network Open, 3(2), e1920294. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.20294</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woodside, J., Young, I.S. &amp; McKinley, M.C. (2022) Culturally adapting the Mediterranean diet pattern&#x2014;a way of promoting more 'sustainable' dietary change? The British Journal of Nutrition, 128(4), 693&#x2013;703. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1017/s0007114522001945</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, D., Fu, L., Pan, D., Lu, Y., Yang, C., Wang, Y. et&#xa0;al. (2021) Role of whole grain consumption in Glycaemic control of diabetic patients: a systematic review and meta&#x2010;analysis of randomized controlled trials. Nutrients, 14, 109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Younossi, Z.M., Blissett, D., Blissett, R., Henry, L., Stepanova, M., Younossi, Y. et&#xa0;al. (2016) The economic and clinical burden of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease in the United States and Europe. Hepatology, 64(5), 1577&#x2013;1586. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1002/hep.28785</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Younossi, Z.M., Koenig, A.B., Abdelatif, D., Fazel, Y., Henry, L. &amp; Wymer, M. (2016) Global epidemiology of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease&#x2010;meta&#x2010;analytic assessment of prevalence, incidence, and outcomes. Hepatology, 64(1), 73&#x2013;84. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1002/hep.28431</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Younossi, Z.M., Stepanova, M., Ong, J., Yilmaz, Y., Duseja, A., Eguchi, Y. et&#xa0;al. (2019) Effects of alcohol consumption and metabolic syndrome on mortality in patients with nonalcoholic and alcohol&#x2010;related fatty liver disease. Clinical Gastroenterology and Hepatology, 17(8), 1625&#x2013;1633.e1621. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cgh.2018.11.033</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Younossi, Z.M., Zelber&#x2010;Sagi, S., Henry, L. &amp; Gerber, L.H. (2023) Lifestyle interventions in nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. Nature Reviews. Gastroenterology &amp; Hepatology, 20(11), 708&#x2013;722. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1038/s41575&#x2010;023&#x2010;00800&#x2010;4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuzbashian, E., Fernando, D.N., Pakseresht, M., Eurich, D.T. &amp; Chan, C.B. (2023) Dairy product consumption and risk of non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease: a systematic review and meta&#x2010;analysis of observational studies. Nutrition, Metabolism, and Cardiovascular Diseases, 33(8), 1461&#x2013;1471. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.numecd.2023.04.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zelber&#x2010;Sagi, S., Ivancovsky&#x2010;Wajcman, D., Fliss Isakov, N., Webb, M., Orenstein, D., Shibolet, O. et&#xa0;al. (2018) High red and processed meat consumption is associated with non&#x2010;alcoholic fatty liver disease and insulin resistance. Journal of Hepatology, 68(6), 1239&#x2013;1246. Available from: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhep.2018.01.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zupo, R., Castellana, F., Crupi, P., Desantis, A., Rondanelli, M., Corbo, F. et&#xa0;al. (2023) Olive oil polyphenols improve HDL cholesterol and promote maintenance of lipid metabolism: a systematic review and meta&#x2010;analysis of randomized controlled trials. Metabolites, 13(12), 1187. Available from: https://doi.org/10.3390/metabo13121187</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>